Guide to the Ann Preston Bridgers Papers, 1871-1967 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ann Preston Bridgers papers 1871-1967 and undated
Bridgers, Ann Preston, 1891-1967
8.8 linear feet Extent: 3,100 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00150
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Ann Preston Bridgers (1891-1967) actress, playwright, and patron of the arts were acquired by the Rubenstein Library through purchase in 1974, and gift in 2012.
Biographical Note
1891, May 1 Born Raleigh, Wake County, North Carolina
ca. 1908 Attended Mary Baldwin Seminary, Staunton, Va.
1915 A.B., Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
1919 Member of the Smith College Unit of the YMCA that served overseas with the Rolling Canteen
1923-1930 Wrote weekly column, Impressions Along Broadway for the Raleigh News and Observer
ca. 1923 Served as understudy to Lynn Fontaine in the play Dulcy while it was on tour
1925 Wrote first draft of play Coquette
1926 Acted in play on Broadway called Broadway
1926 Enrolled in English class at Columbia University
1927 Collaborated with George Abbott to bring Coquette starring Helen Hayes to Broadway
1935-1936 Instrumental in founding the Raleigh Little Theater under the auspices of the Federal Theatre Project of the Work Projects Administration
1936 Her play Quicksand was presented by the Raleigh Little Theater
1936-1937 Wrote column The Theatre for the Raleigh Times
1937 Her play Coquette was performed by the Raleigh Little Theater
1938 Her play Carrie Was a Lady was performed by the Raleigh Little Theatre
1965-1966 Member of the Raleigh Little Theater Board of Directors
1967, May 3 Died
Collection Overview
The papers of Ann Preston Bridgers span the years 1871-1967, although the bulk of the material covers the period 1925-1963. Included in the collection are correspondence, manuscript drafts and notes, business items and programs related to the Raleigh Little Theatre, contracts, wills, newsclippings, and photographs.
Miss Bridgers' life is best documented in the correspondence. It is chiefly of a personal nature, between Miss Bridgers and her family, including her sisters Elizabeth (Bab) and Emily and to a lesser extent her brother Robert. Elizabeth was the wife of Jonathan Daniels, son of Josephus Daniels, and there are several letters from Jonathan to the Bridgers and references made to his parents. Later correspondence includes letters from Bab's daughter, Elizabeth and her husband Charles (Chick) B. Squire, in which they often critiqued each other's writings.
Elizabeth Lawrence, horticulturist and author of gardening works, is also represented extensively in the correspondence from the mid 1930's until about 1948. Other correspondents include George Abbott, whose correspondence dates primarily from 1962 to 1964, and various literary agents.
The Writings series comprises the bulk of the collection, and includes works by Miss Bridgers and other members of her family and friends. Coquette, the work for which she is best known is not represented in this series. There is, however, information regarding this play, which opened on Broadway in 1927, in the Correspondence, Legal and Financial Papers, Raleigh Little Theater, and Clippings series. Also included in this series are several drafts of Those Without Freedom, an unpublished novel about the South after the Civil War.
The National Union Catalog Pre-1956 Imprints lists two published works by Miss Bridgers: Coquette, where she is listed as the joint author, and an article in the Saturday Review of Literature in 1935 about Thomas Wolfe. Drafts and background material for this article are located in the Writings series. Other persons represented in the Writings series include: Emily and Robert R. Bridgers; Elizabeth (Daniels) Squire; and Elizabeth Lawrence.
The efforts of Miss Bridgers and others involved with the founding of the Raleigh Little Theater are reflected in the Correspondence and Raleigh Little Theater series.
In addition to legal papers relating to the play Coquette, the Legal and Financial Papers series also includes documents concerning the will and estate of Miss Bridgers' aunt, Emily Bridgers, receipts, and other miscellaneous financial data. Financial concerns of the family are also found in the Correspondence series.
The Clippings series contains reviews of the Broadway production of Coquette, as well as book reviews and newspaper columns by Miss Bridgers. The series also provides information about Miss Bridgers, other family members, and miscellany items.
Genealogical information about the Bridgers family, an engagement book Miss Bridgers kept while traveling in Europe (1961), and other items comprise the Miscellany series.
The Photographs series contains three albums of photographs. Some appear to be of theatrical productions; many are of unidentified persons. Loose photographs include those of Ann Preston Bridgers, George Abbott, Mr. and Mrs. Josephus Daniels, and Miss Bridgers' grandfather, Robert Rufus Bridgers.
Subject Headings
Bridgers Family; Bridgers, Ann Preston; Raleigh Little Theater (Raleigh, N.C.); Lawrence, Elizabeth, 1904-1985; Abbott, George, 1889-; Daniels, Jonathan, 1902-; Authors, American; Theater -- North Carolina; Federal Theater Project (U.S.)
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1887-1967 and undated
  Chiefly personal correspondence between Bridgers family members and friends. Includes letters from agents, who were attempting to get Miss Bridgers' plays produced and her writings published. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1887-1929, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1930-1939, (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1940-1945, (6 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1946-1957, (8 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1958-1966 and undated, (8 folders) (Box 5)
- Writings Series
  Divided into two subseries, those by Miss Bridgers and those by others. Those by Miss Bridgers are subarranged alphabetically by title, while those by others are subarranged alphabetically by author. Also includes miscellaneous notes, writings, and drafts of unidentified manuscripts.
  - Ann P. Bridgers Writings Subseries
    - Alice and the Duchess-Swing It or Pig and Peppers Misc. Notes and Mss. (Box 6)
    - Carrie Was a Lady, Misc. Notes and Mss. of Version entitled Once A Virgin (Box 6)
    - Carrie Was a Lady Mss. of Play, Version 1 (Box 6)
    - Carrie Was a Lady Mss. of Play, Version 2 (Box 6)
    - Carrie Was a Lady Mss. of Play, Version 3 (Box 6)
    - David and King Saul Misc. Notes and Mss. of Play, (4 folders) (Box 6)
    - David and King Saul Mss. of Play (Box 6)
    - Henrietta Opera, Mss. and Pages Which were cut (Box 7)
    - Henrietta Opera, Mss. (Box 7)
    - Henrietta Opera, Mss. First Copy (Box 7)
    - It's Not Always Easy Play, Mss. of Version entitled It Isn't Always Easy (Box 7)
    - It's Not Always Easy Mss. of Play (Box 7)
    - Lindsay Harper Notes and Mss. of Play (Box 7)
    - Lindsay Harper Mss. of Play (Box 7)
    - Mark of Murder Misc. Notes and Mss. (Box 7)
    - Mrs. John Emerson Version Entitled Quicksand (Box 7)
    - Mrs. John Emerson Version Entitled Mrs. John Latimer (Box 7)
    - Mrs. John Emerson Mss. of Play, Version 1 (Box 8)
    - Mrs. John Emerson Mss. of Play, Version 2 (Box 8)
    - New York 1918 Mss. of Play, Version 1 (Box 8)
    - New York 1918 Mss. of Play, Version 2 (Box 8)
    - New York 1918 Mss. of Play, Version 3 (Box 8)
    - November 8, 1942 Misc. Notes and Radio Script, 1943 (Box 8)
    - A Play About America Today, the Particular Scene Being the South Version Entitled Break This Heavy Chain (Box 8)
    - A Play About America Today, the Particular Scene Being the South Mss. With Notes 1940 (Box 8)
    - A Play About America Today, the Particular Scene Being the South Mss. 1940 (Box 8)
    - Possess These Shores Mss. of Play, Version 1 (Box 8)
    - Possess These Shores Mss. of Play, Version 2 (Box 8)
    - Possess These Shores Mss. of Play, Version 3 (Box 8)
    - The Same House (Box 9)
    - Shanty Boat, The Theatre Background Material, Drawings and Notes (Box 9)
    - The Theatre Incl. Dance This Beautiful Structure Version Entitled Calhoun (Box 9)
    - This Beautiful Structure Long Version This Beautiful Structure Short Version, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - This Beautiful Structure Edited Version, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - This Throne of Kings Working Notes (Box 10)
    - This Throne of Kings Misc. Notes and Mss., (5 folders) (Box 10)
    - This Throne of Kings Mss. of Play (Box 10)
    - Those Without Freedom Misc. Notes and Mss., Version 1, (5 folders) (Box 11)
    - Those Without Freedom Misc. Notes and Mss., Version 2, (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - Those Without Freedom Misc. Notes and Mss., Version 2, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Those Without Freedom Version 1, Chapters 1-17, (5 folders) (Box 12)
    - Those Without Freedom Version 1, Edited Pages (Box 12)
    - Those Without Freedom Version 2, Chapters 1-17, (5 folders) (Box 13)
    - Those Without Freedom Version 3, Chapters 1-17, (4 folders) (Box 13)
    - Those Without Freedom Notes (Box 13)
    - Those Without Freedom Mss. of Play (Box 13)
    - Those Without Freedom Omitted Last Chapters (Box 13)
    - Tine Mss. of Play, Edited Version 1, (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Tine Mss. of Play, Edited Version 2 (Box 14)
    - Tine Mss. of Play (Box 14)
    - When I Love Thee Not Mss. and Notes, Version 1 (Box 14)
    - When I Love Thee Not Mss., Version 2 (Box 14)
    - When I Love Thee Not Mss. and Notes, Version 3 (Box 14)
    - Who Help Themselves Mss. Fragment (Box 14)
    - Who Treads the Boards (Box 14)
    - Wolfe, Thomas - Background Material for Published Magazine Article Thomas Wolfe and the Article (Box 15)
    - Misc. Mss., (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Misc. Notes and Mss., (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Unidentified, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Writings of Others Subseries
    - Bridgers, Emily N. (Box 16)
      - Misc. (Box 16)
    - Bridgers, Robert R.
      - Driftwood (Box 16)
      - "Easter" (Box 16)
      - The Golden Rods Misc. Notes and Mss. Version 1 (Box 16)
      - The Golden Rods Mss. Version 2 (Box 16)
      - Ogeechee Swamp Notes and Mss. Version 1, (3 folders) (Box 16)
      - Ogeechee Swamp Mss. Version 2, (3 folders) (Box 17)
      - Ogeechee Swamp Mss. of Play by Katherine Simons from the Story by Robert R. Bridgers (Box 17)
      - Old Man Gooch Misc. Notes and Mss. (Box 17)
      - Yellow Gal Mss. (Box 17)
      - Untitled Mss., 1938 (Box 17)
    - Lawrence, Elizabeth L.
      - Articles on Gardening (Box 17)
      - Misc. (Box 17)
    - Squire, Elizabeth B. Daniels
      - Carolina--Two Families The Feud; The Castle (Box 17)
      - Rhoda (Box 17)
      - A Touch of Meanness Misc. Notes and Mss. (Box 18)
      - A Touch of Meanness Mss. (Box 18)
      - Mss. Title Unidentified, (3 folders) (Box 18)
      - Unidentified Notes and Mss., (2 folders) (Box 18)
      - Unidentified Notes and Mss., (2 folders) (Box 19)
      - Misc. Notes and Mss., (3 folders) (Box 19)
    - Willis, Winifred
      - Byron (Box 19)
    - Unidentified Authors (Box 19)
- Raleigh Little Theater Series
  Divided into three subseries: General, 1936-1966; Programs, 1936-1966; and Clippings, 1936-1965. Includes information about different artists, plays, and people responsible for its theatrical productions, board minutes, a list of its patrons, a draft of its history, and other miscellany items. Arranged chronologically within each subseries.
  - General, 1936-1966 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Programs, 1936-1966, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Clippings, 1936-1965 and undated (Box 20)
- Legal and Financial Papers Series
  Divided into three subseries: Coquette, 1926-1933; Emily Bridgers Estate, 1924-1944; and Miscellany, 1913-1959, and undated. Includes legal matters relating to the play Coquette; the will and estate of Miss Bridgers' aunt, Emily Bridgers; receipts and furniture inventories; and other miscellaneous items. Arranged chronologically within each subseries.
  - Coquette, 1926-1933 (Box 20)
  - Emily Bridgers Estate, 1924-1944 (Box 20)
  - Miscellany, 1913-1959 and undated Clippings (Box 20)
- Clippings Series
  Divided into five subseries: Book reviews; Coquette; Impressions Along Broadway; The Theatre; and Miscellany. The book reviews and columns Impressions Along Broadway and The Theatre were written by Miss Bridgers. The Coquette clippings include reviews of the Broadway production of the play (1927) from various newspapers and of its star Helen Hayes. Includes miscellaneous clippings relating to Miss Bridgers, her family, and other topics. Arranged chronologically within each subseries.
  - Book Reviews, 1925-1937 (Box 20)
  - Coquette, 1927-1965 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 20)
  - Impressions Along Broadway, 1923-1930 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 21)
  - The Theatre, 1936-1937 and undated (Box 21)
  - Miscellany, 1925-1966 and undated (Box 21)
- Miscellany Series, 1871-1961 and undated
  Includes Miss Bridgers' passport, engagement book, genealogical information about the Bridgers family, and other miscellaneous items. Arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellany (Box 21)
- Photographs Series
  Includes three photograph albums and a few loose photographs primarily of the Bridgers family.
  - Albums (Box 21)
  - Albums, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Miscellany (Box 22)